I used to be very passionate and excited.
嗯变得从以前是的非常的热血亢奋
But now I've become much calmer.
上头变成现在冷静了很多
Firstly, as the saying goes, a good warrior doesn't seek glory.
首先我们说这个善战者无赫赫之功啊
It's often said that a general's fame is built on countless lives lost.
通常说一将成名万骨枯
Many times, if you engage in war too aggressively,
很多的时候如果你特别的穷兵动武
you can indeed leave behind a glorious record of battles.
你是能留下赫赫战功
You'll be remembered in history
是能青史留名
But what kind of life will you leave behind?
但是你将留下的是一个什么样的生活呢
Right?
对不对
Well, how do you put it?
那个怎么说呢
Since ancient times, the dead have been left unburied
古来白骨无人收啊
It's just a matter of a few millimeters
十毫厘矣啊
And there's the Ballad of Mulan
还有这个这个这个这个木兰辞
Often depicting the chaotic war years
很多时候写的这个战乱年代的
The people's lives were truly miserable
人民生活是非常惨的
If I were in today's Russia
假如我是今天俄罗斯的
Or a 40-year-old male from Ukraine
或者是乌克兰的40岁男性
I'd most likely be arrested on my way to the internet cafe
我大概率在去网吧的路上就被抓走了
Right?
对不对
This is extremely painful
这个非常的痛苦
So I used to think, oh
所以以前我总认为哎呀
Why doesn't our country use its good weapons
咱们国家怎么有好武器的不使啊
We need to show off our strength too My mindset shifted right away. When you really have to pay the price You don't think that way anymore So much of the time, I feel that peace and development are the prevailing trends. Still, these are the things that the world has developed today.
然后这个东西咱们也得秀肌肉啊 我的思维一下就转变过来了啊 当你真正需要付出代价的时候 你就不这么想 所以很多的时候 我觉得和平发展才是一个大势所趋 还是今天这世界发展出来这些东西呢
We have the capability to destroy the world,
咱们有毁灭世界的能力
but we use it to benefit humanity.
但咱们用来造福人类
This is truly the greatest good.
这才是真正的啊善之善
The good person wins without fighting.
善者不战而屈人之兵
This is the most powerful approach.
这是最厉害的
After all, even if you can fight, what does it achieve?
因为一旦你能打又能怎么样呢
Wouldn't that just result in countless casualties?
这是不是就是大家就一片一片白骨而已
It has no practical significance
没有任何的实际意义
So, to explain
所以来讲的话
What does it mean to follow the will of heaven?
什么叫顺应天命
What does that even mean?
什么叫那什么呢
It means to ensure the people can live in peace and prosperity
就是让老百姓啊安居乐业
To make sure everyone can survive
让大家都能活下去啊
This is known as the way of sustenance
这叫什么生生之道
To let life thrive
let live live啊
It’s about ensuring the continuity of life
那就让生命能够延续下去
This is the most crucial aspect
这是最关键的东西
So, in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
when we're young,
年轻的时候啊
why is this so?
为什么是这样呢
Because in our youth, we're full of passion,
因为年轻的时候呢啊一腔热血
driven by hormones and genes,
他这个激素跟这个基因的作用
we want to tear things down,
他就想破坏东西
we want to destroy,
他就想毁灭
yet we also want to achieve great things,
他又想建功立业
but our achievements often come at the cost of our peers,
但是你的建功立业呢往往建立在同胞啊
with the loss of many lives.
同类大量死亡的基础上
In the end, who can truly live on after the war is over? In reality, your social status remains the same, you just drag your wounded body, and return to your Russian hometown.
到最后谁又能活在战争的结束呢 是不是实际上来讲 你的社会地位该是怎样还是怎样 你也就拖着个伤残的身躯 然后回到了那个俄罗斯的家乡
Often, that's how it is.
对对很多的时候就是这样
So today we need to look at many aspects to discuss,
所以我们要今天要看很多东西来讲
whether fighting a war to the bitter end is the right choice.
穷病毒武到底是不是一个正确的一个选择
Generally speaking, it's not.
通常来讲的话不是
and whether the people can have enough to eat.
而让人民能不能吃上饱饭
to ensure the people live and work in peace and contentment
能让人民安居乐业
then everyone remains calm
然后大家呢不急躁
and doesn’t feel overly worried about these issues
不因为这些东西呢感觉到很忧虑啊
a strong national defense
强大的国防
robust public security
强大的治安
all these things speak for themselves
这个东西来背后来讲话
all of which have been achieved at a tremendous cost by countless individuals
都是无数人付出了特别大的代价才达到的
so it’s not something that’s easily attained
所以不是那么简简单单的东西
so what one pursues in their youth
所以年轻的时候追求的东西
is entirely different from what they value when they grow older
跟那个上了岁数完全不一样
When you really start to age
等你真的上了岁数啊
you start to take charge
这个开始当家了
you don't realize it until you're in charge
不当家不知道啊
how expensive the necessities of life can be
油盐柴米贵啊
Often, as your parents get older
很多的时候你像父母岁数大了
they fall ill due to old age
年迈生病了
you also have to take your children to the pediatric hospital
孩子也在陪孩子去儿研所啊
to get an appointment at the children's hospital
儿童医院挂个号啊
the emergency queue numbers go into the thousands
排的那个急诊都几千号
reaching four digits
都四位数的时候
You really get a sense of what despair feels like. And at this moment, a middle-aged person is overwhelmed by the weight of life. Unlike when they were young and could feed themselves and ensure the whole family wasn't hungry. You have that constant feeling of being in the phase of wanting to mate and make money.
你就真能感觉到什么东西叫绝望了啊 而这个时候的一个中年人 他被生活的重担所压垮 不像年轻的时候一人吃饱 全家不饿啊 你天天那种感觉 还是在一种交配和这个赚钱的冲动期
You're broke but still want to mate.
你又没钱又想交配
Then you just feel
然后就觉得哎呀
that the world is so unfair.
这世界真不公
I need to have my own space
我得有一片自己的天地
I need to have my own something
我得有一片那什么东西
But you'll find that modern economic life is quite complex
但你会发现现代的经济生活是很复杂的
So you've made a good plan
所以你进行了良好的规划
When you have a precise grasp of it
进行了准确的把握的时候
You can make your life exceptionally wonderful
你可以把自己的生活变得特别美好啊
So speaking of it
所以来讲的话
This is the purpose of my writing books and making videos.
这才是我写书做视频的目的
It's to guide everyone towards a healthier
就是来讲引导大家走向一个比较健康的
More sustainable kind of development
比较可持续的一种发展
Rather than just rushing into things without thinking
而不是说啊一急了就怎么着
Or making hasty decisions in a moment of frustration
一拍大腿就怎么怎么着
Instead of getting lost in grand narratives
而不是那种陷于宏大叙事的
An idealized projection of one's own future
对自己个人未来的一种理想化推断
A mere imagination
一种想象
That's not very meaningful
那没有意思
Only by living a good personal life
只有把个人的生活过好了以后
Can it truly be considered a good life
那才算是真正的一种好的生活
So, based on this premise
所以我们从这个基础上来讲
Let's look at some historical figures
再看一些历史人物
We'll understand it then.
我们就能明白了
In fact, many historical figures, like Jia Xu, were similar.
其实很多历史人物像贾诩这样的人
He was genuinely smart. Because he knew how to diminish the ambitions of the heroes across the land during the late Eastern Han Dynasty. There were so many aristocrats. So many people wanted to seize control of provinces and commanderies. Wanted to deceive the world and steal fame. Wanted to claim titles and rule as lone wolves. These people were so repulsive.
他是真聪明 因为他知道在东汉末年削天下英雄之心 有这么多贵族 有这么多人想去偷取州郡 想去欺世盗名 想去称孤道寡 这些人好恶心好恶心
Right?
对不对
Those people are actually no longer necessary.
那些人其实就没有什么存在的必要了吧
That led to Li Juo's death.
那引李觉国死
Killing the nobles and officials in Chang'an.
杀这个这个长安当中的这个王公大臣啊
Causing the Eastern Han court to fall apart.
让这个东汉朝廷完蛋
And killing ambitious figures like Cao Cao.
又杀这样曹操这样的野心家
Then making him fall apart as well.
然后让他的也完蛋
Cao Ang, the successor, also met the same fate.
那曹昂昂这样继承人也完蛋
So, to put it simply,
所以其实来讲的话
Jia Xu has undermined many nobles throughout his life.
贾诩他一生之中坑坑了很多贵族
But he never undermined the common people.
他没有坑老百姓
That's why after World War II and the invention of nuclear weapons,
所以这就是为什么二战以后发明了核武器以后
the number of wars actually decreased.
战争数量反而下降了
It's mostly major powers bullying smaller countries.
都是大国欺负小国
There are rarely direct conflicts between two major powers.
很少有正常的两强相较啊
Mostly, it's proxy wars.
都是代理人战争
Why is this the case?
为什么是这样呢
Because the initiators of war can now be easily destroyed.
因为就是战争的发动者可以被轻易的毁灭了
So once the initiators of war can be easily destroyed,
所以战争的发动者一旦可以被轻易毁灭了
once that becomes the cost,
他一旦成为了这个代价了以后
many people decide it's not worth starting a war.
所以很多人就觉得那那就不发动战争了
Let's call it the final battle. Don't say defeat. Always say the final battle. This is where many people are hypocritical. So this really hits a nerve with humans when it comes to the pain that is felt personally. When someone says war is necessary,
那就终战吧 不说战败 一定说终战 这就是很多人虚伪之处 所以这个东西真是到了人类的这个 切肤之痛的时候 就是说什么战争是必须的的话
If the war starters themselves had to die,
如果让战争的发动者自己死掉的话
Would the war still be necessary?
那这战争还是不是必须的了
So that's how it all works out.
所以这一切东西就是这样
When you make the first move in a game of Chinese chess,
你在下象棋的第一步的时候
the two generals see each other right away.
两个老将就互相看见了
Whoever sees the other first can fly and eliminate them.
谁就把谁给飞死了
Then the game is over.
那这个游戏就结束了
So everything is based on the generals, the commanders,
所以一切都是以这个啊这个老将老帅啊
ending the game with their capture as the fundamental outcome.
完蛋为这个结结果为这个基础的
This is why after the invention of nuclear weapons,
所以这就是核武器发明以后
the number of human wars has drastically decreased.
为什么人类的战争的数量急剧的下降了
In ancient times, kings lived in castles,
因为以前古代战争国王都住在城堡里边啊
surrounded by layers of their own royal guards.
层层的这个有自己的侍卫军
They have their own personal guards
有自己的亲卫队
So they won't be harmed in the slightest
所以不会伤及到他们丝毫啊
Therefore, the so-called pain is
所以来讲的话所谓的切肤之痛
For them, the common people are like clothes or fur
那老百姓对他们来讲就如衣服如皮毛一样啊
It won't hurt their bones
是不会伤筋动骨
Their own nobles
自己的贵族
These Kshatriyas are their own
自己的这些杀帝利们才是自己的
How should I put it
这个这个怎么说呢
The foundation of their rule
自己的这个统治的基础
These Eight Banners
这些八旗
These monks These Attendant Guard and Imperial Army troops are the foundation of my own strength. These Tian Ce generals So in many cases, it won't harm themselves He just wants to fight
这些蒙克 这些这个确削这些侍卫亲军都是自己的基础 这些天策上将 所以很多的时候来讲不会伤及到自身 他就想打
Once they get hurt
一旦伤及到自身
He doesn't want to fight anymore
他就不想打
Actually, you can see I've transformed from a passionate young man
其实你看我从一个热血青年转变成一个啊
Into a straightforward middle-aged person as well
老老实实的中年也是这样
Truly understanding
真正明白了
One day you might start a war yourself
有一天自己可能会开战
When the first wave dies
第一波死的时候
you won’t be trying to persuade these people anymore
你就不会劝这些了
Many people always think about being doomsday preppers
很多人总是去啊想这个末日准备狂
Always think about the end of the world
总是想在世界末日的时候
thinking they could make it through
自己能够生存下来
but in reality, you’d just be one of the 10 trillion zombies
实际上你就是10万亿僵尸当中的一个啊
right?
对不对
So, what I’m saying is
所以就是说这个东西
once you become the victim
一旦就是你作为受害的一方呢
You wouldn't think that way.
你就不会这么想
What's known as the track theory.
所谓的轨道理论
If you were there,
如果你是在那
Whether it's five people or one person,
甭管是五人还是一个人
You're the one tied to the track.
你是在轨道上被捆的那个人
You wouldn't think that way anymore.
你就不这么想了啊
When it comes to boosting the economy,
一说活跃经济
If it comes at your expense,
如果以你为代价
You wouldn't think that way.
你就不会这么想了
So everything depends on who the starting point is.
所以这一切的一切看以谁为出发点
So no matter what
所以无论怎么样
If those songs praising war are necessary
如果那些歌颂战争很必要
These things that seem so sweet
这些东西很甜蜜的人
Let him try going to the battlefield himself
那让他自己去上战场试一试
Face the landmines head-on Fight against the drones Would he still think the same way In many cases at that time We would say the world isn't as terrifying as it seems When the day comes
一刀一枪的去跟地雷滚一滚 去跟无人机搏斗一下 他会不会这么想 那个时候很多时候来讲 我们就讲这世界来讲就没有那么的可怕了 当有一天的时候
This person doesn't have to step onto the battlefield
这个人不用走上战场
It's all about machines competing against each other
都是一些机器去比拼的时候
So I believe people will definitely be liberated in this way
所以我觉得人那样就一定能够解放出来
But that's not necessarily the case
那么也未必
Because only when those who initiate wars are deterred from doing so easily
因为只有让战争的发动者不敢轻易的发动战争
Can true peace for humanity truly be achieved
这个时候人类的和平才能真正的到来
So we often say
所以还讲我们一直说啊
A skilled warrior doesn't seek glory
善战者没有赫赫之功
When it comes to it, though
很周的时候来讲的话
Although it means maintaining peace
虽然来说平定这个啊
Eliminate the one who replaced and eradicated
杀掉那个取代那个灭绝
This feels like a great achievement
这个感觉到很有功劳
It's quite something
很那什么
But history has given these figures too much
但是历史上给这些人物太多的啊
Too much credit
太多的credits
Too much, how to say, glory
太多的这种怎么说荣耀了
And the ones who truly made a difference without their presence
而真正那些没有因为他的存在
Without launching large-scale wars
没有发动大型战争
Because of their presence
因为他的存在
People are very content
人民很和啊
It's truly harmonious
非常的和谐
People live and work in peace and contentment
安居乐业
This is the true great achievement of history
这才是真正的历史的伟大功绩
That is to say
也就是说来讲的话
He loves the people
仁爱人民
People live and work in peace and contentment
安居居乐业
This is the greatest merit
这才是最伟大的功劳
Instead of exhausting resources on military might
而不是穷兵独武
Exhausting resources on military might
穷兵直武
In the end, they will all end up in utter defeat
最终都将一败涂地